This material is made available to you by or on
NOTE CONF
behalf of the University of Melbourne under section 113P of
the Copyright Act 1968.
NOTE CONF
It may be subject to copyright.
For more information, visit the university copyright website.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Um, Good morning.
NOTE CONF
I'm going to be running a, um, sorry, I don't
know if this is, you can hear me.
NOTE CONF
Somebody's walked off with the regular lapel mic.
Uh, can you hear me at the back?
NOTE CONF
Yeah, OK, fantastic.
So I'm going to be running a slightly shorter lecture
NOTE CONF
today cause there's an exam running from 12 to 3,
and I'm the only invigilator, so I have to rush
NOTE CONF
to the other side of the campus to administer the
exam.
NOTE CONF
So in order to get there on time, I'll, I
might stop 5 minutes earlier, um, than normal.
NOTE CONF
The um Topic of the week is around threat actors
and So what's a threat?
NOTE CONF
What's a threat actor?
What's an attack?
NOTE CONF
And I'm going to talk about the asymmetry between the
threat actor and the defender.
NOTE CONF
That's going to be sort of the main underlying theme.
And my quote for the week is amateurs, hack systems,
NOTE CONF
professionals, hack people.
Amateurs hack systems and professionals hack people.
NOTE CONF
Something to think about.
What it's trying to a lot of people, when they
NOTE CONF
read the quote, they think, Oh, that means that it's
not enough to build cyber defenses around digital technology.
NOTE CONF
You need to create awareness around people because people can
be phished, they can be spear phished, they can be.
NOTE CONF
Uh, manipulated, uh, when they're using a computer, they click
on the right thing, etc.
NOTE CONF
and that's a very weak reading of this quote.
There's a much, much stronger reading, a much more deeper
NOTE CONF
reading which says.
Amateurs may grind against the control stack, the defensive architecture
NOTE CONF
that you've built in the digital environment.
A professional will not.
NOTE CONF
They might.
You know they will not spend a lot of time
NOTE CONF
trying to find a vulnerability in your digital systems, weaponize
that vulnerability, and hope that they can penetrate your organization
NOTE CONF
before it gets patched.
They would rather find an individual in the organization that
NOTE CONF
will be only too happy to help them.
So you can patch systems, but how do you patch
NOTE CONF
an employee that's very helpful?
To the wrong person, right?
NOTE CONF
So the entire, what it's arguing, what, what I would
say the quote is pointing to more substantively, is that
NOTE CONF
your organization's cyber or your organization's security program, if it's
centered around stopping Attackers from getting in the digital environment,
NOTE CONF
then maybe you need to look broader at the whole
organization and not just in the digital environment.
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, I'm gonna talk about Assignment 2, very quickly.
NOTE CONF
Uh, everybody knows that it's been released.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
Fantastic.
Um, 6 people per group, and you're gonna sign up
NOTE CONF
into your group in your tutorials this week.
So every tutor has a signup sheet that you're gonna
NOTE CONF
go in and sign your name and your group's names
in.
NOTE CONF
20 minutes is the presentation you're giving.
I've asked all the tutors not to answer any questions
NOTE CONF
about assignment 2.
Like, do not answer any questions about assignment 2.
NOTE CONF
Why?
Because I don't want tutors to start giving helpful comments
NOTE CONF
that are taken as requirements, and then people come later
and say, but my tutor said.
NOTE CONF
So, tutors, you are not to say anything about what
the assignments requirements are.
NOTE CONF
Don't be helpful, right?
You're not helping, you're hurting, OK?
NOTE CONF
So all questions directed to me.
Either by email to me or better by posting on
NOTE CONF
the discussion thread for the subject, where I will deal
with them directly.
NOTE CONF
OK, so you have 20 minutes for your presentation.
Not everybody in your group needs to present.
NOTE CONF
OK, so if there's 6 people in the group, don't
try to have 6 people stand up and, you know,
NOTE CONF
just the jarring effect of 6 different accents or 6
different voices trying to speak to the same thing in
NOTE CONF
20 minutes, you know.
Choose your best 2 to 3 speakers, but make sure
NOTE CONF
that you divide your work across the group in a
fair way.
NOTE CONF
You need to have sources, at least 2 academic, 2
industry.
NOTE CONF
Put the sources in the slides.
The slides get submitted.
NOTE CONF
We'll check the sources.
Week 5 is when the presentations happen.
NOTE CONF
No, you cannot say, Can I go first, 2nd or
3rd?
NOTE CONF
Everybody needs to be ready in week 5.
The tutors decide who to call up.
NOTE CONF
And if there's more groups that can fit in week
5, then they spill over to week 6, and no,
NOTE CONF
you cannot say, can I go in week 6 because
blah blah blah, right?
NOTE CONF
So unless there is an AAP adjusted program or some
official reason why you cannot make it, you're expected to
NOTE CONF
all be there.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Now, what the assignment asks you to do is to
pick one of these 5 challenges threat actor response, asset
NOTE CONF
protection enhancement, size or effectiveness, risk communication, incident preparedness, right?
And this is a research and development assignment.
NOTE CONF
It's not a hey, go hit the textbook and try
to find in the 1st, 2nd or 3rd week's material,
NOTE CONF
where did we cover these.
No, this is a you go out and knowing what
NOTE CONF
you know from the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd week, now
do an R&D assignment where you try to act, try
NOTE CONF
to find a problem that is real in the world.
And try to find a solution to that problem that
NOTE CONF
you can pitch to your audience.
The problem needs to come from one of these categories
NOTE CONF
that you've got on your left, A to E, but
the problem's the solution's got to look like either a
NOTE CONF
process, a technology, a management policy or procedure or framework,
or a behavioral mechanism, something, some solution that fits in
NOTE CONF
those categories.
So problem from the left, solution from the right, and
NOTE CONF
you need to use the triplet model to explain to
us why this is a problem.
NOTE CONF
So that is really important.
In your 20 minute presentation, you have 4 minutes on
NOTE CONF
the problem, 10 minutes on the innovation that you're pitching,
4 minutes on how you plan to implement it, and
NOTE CONF
2 minutes for Q&A, OK?
So the point here is, on the left-hand side, choose
NOTE CONF
a problem that fits in those categories, in one of
those categories, or more.
NOTE CONF
Choose a solution that you're pitching that comes from the
right.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Now, I'm going to give you an example.
NOTE CONF
This is my, this is what I would do.
So somebody said to me, hey, you're doing this, go
NOTE CONF
ahead now, pitch.
I'm not going to do the whole thing, but just
NOTE CONF
to give you an idea of how this works, I
might say, hey, the problem that organizations have right now
NOTE CONF
is they have a lot of knowledge that's really valuable,
but they don't know where it is.
NOTE CONF
They don't know where it is, they don't know who
has it.
NOTE CONF
They don't know which teams have it fragmented amongst each
other.
NOTE CONF
They just can't find it, right?
Now, what I'm, what I'm saying is when there's this
NOTE CONF
deep problem where you don't know what knowledge you have,
and you have these business partners or suppliers or contractors
NOTE CONF
who are connecting with your organization, you normally connect them
by saying, OK, what system do you need access to?
NOTE CONF
And then you give them a username and password, and
they proceed to connect with your organizational systems and through
NOTE CONF
that username and password they have access to your internal
environment where there's a lot of knowledge sitting but nobody's
NOTE CONF
monitoring.
So my solution here is, or my problem articulation here
NOTE CONF
is you don't want to give people access purely on
the basis of systems.
NOTE CONF
You want to say what knowledge do they have access
to when they come to my firm.
NOTE CONF
This is the problem, right?
You don't know what knowledge they have access to because
NOTE CONF
you're just looking at the system.
You don't know what's in the system.
NOTE CONF
You don't know what information is stored in those file
systems.
NOTE CONF
You give them access and you have no idea what
they can actually learn and what they can take away
NOTE CONF
from it.
So the solution is a knowledge map.
NOTE CONF
That's my innovation.
What is a knowledge map.
NOTE CONF
A big two dimensional map where you go into your
organization, you basically categorize inventorize all the infinite knowledge, you
NOTE CONF
put it in the map, and then you give it
to the SISO and whenever somebody comes in, you ask
NOTE CONF
the CISO to check to see whether the knowledge that
this person needs to get access to is the only
NOTE CONF
knowledge they have access to, or do they have more
and what might they do with it.
NOTE CONF
OK, so that knowledge map becomes your central artifact around
which you give people access.
NOTE CONF
Now, if I, and then I would say, if I
could do this, if I could implement it by giving
NOTE CONF
the CISO this artifact and build it and refresh it
every 6 months, now when somebody comes in as a
NOTE CONF
business partner.
Becomes a competitor, switches.
NOTE CONF
The knowledge map is my key trigger point by which
I can line up trip wires.
NOTE CONF
If you have access to A but you try to
access B, it's going to set an alarm, and we're
NOTE CONF
going to query our relationship with you and we're going
to cut you off if we find that your behavior
NOTE CONF
looks more like a competitor than a partner.
So that's my solution to the Huawei versus T-Mobile case,
NOTE CONF
as well as a generic solution.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Does that make sense?
See how I pitched it?
NOTE CONF
What's the problem?
And I mean I didn't use a triplet model, but
NOTE CONF
I could clearly say the asset is knowledge.
The threat actor is the competitor slash attacker, and the
NOTE CONF
risk is that they're going to get access to the
knowledge by existing.
NOTE CONF
Authorized access that we give them.
How am I going to put in a control?
NOTE CONF
I'm going to bring in a knowledge asset map.
I'm going to give it to the size.
NOTE CONF
I'm going to create a process by which every time
somebody comes into the firm, it gets checked, and maybe
NOTE CONF
every 3 to 6 months it gets checked to make
sure that their behavior remains consistent.
NOTE CONF
Happy?
Makes it like, sounds like a solution.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, and I would back it up with research references,
etc.
NOTE CONF
So that's the kind of thing that I would pitch,
of course, I'm not expecting you to pitch it exactly
NOTE CONF
like that, but it's just to give you an idea
of the thought process behind it.
NOTE CONF
So you have like a mental model that you can
now mimic, OK?
NOTE CONF
Fantastic.
So, this week in cybersecurity management, We are going to
NOTE CONF
go through module number 3.
I have, on the request of one student who said,
NOTE CONF
Hey, Can you open next week's module because it's way
too much teaching, I'd like to know who did that.
NOTE CONF
Somebody did that, right?
Thank you.
NOTE CONF
So you did a service to everybody, because I opened
up all the modules for the whole subject, right?
NOTE CONF
But what that means is that, um, in every module,
the last page has what you're doing in your tutorial.
NOTE CONF
I was not releasing all of them because I was
updating what's happening in the tutorial, but now I just
NOTE CONF
decided, I'll just let everybody have access to all of
it, but I might still modify that, right?
NOTE CONF
So, whenever you come into a new week, check.
If you haven't looked before, check again to make sure
NOTE CONF
that I haven't updated what's happening in the tutorial, OK.
So you're gonna go through textbook pages 30 to 75,
NOTE CONF
and so there is a bit of a reading to
do and attend the workshop, and in the workshop, we're
NOTE CONF
going to have regular Q&A.
You're gonna register your groups for the assignment.
NOTE CONF
You're gonna go through the 1st 6 scenes of Horizon,
you probably won't get through all of them, maybe the
NOTE CONF
1st 3, but this time, Different from last year, I
have given the tutors the exam questions from last year,
NOTE CONF
C1, C2, C3, which is the last section, the biggest
part of the exam, the one that everybody tends to
NOTE CONF
bomb, and I've said, give the students question one and
question two, the two of the three parts of the
NOTE CONF
exam question, and ask them to apply it on the
horizon, so that they get some, some actual practice on.
NOTE CONF
What the exam is going to ask them, let them
apply on the horizon, and every week we might give
NOTE CONF
them a different scenario.
So hopefully every week when you go in, we'll try
NOTE CONF
to give you a different scenario, apply it, apply it
so that when you get to the exam, you've had
NOTE CONF
10 weeks of answering Section C, so you won't get
like the shock that we had last year.
NOTE CONF
OK, focusing on threat actors.
Focusing on threat actors, the intended learning objectives, deep understanding
NOTE CONF
of threat actors, what's their motivation, what are their methods,
etc.
NOTE CONF
identify a range of threat actors, identify common cyber security
attacks on organizations, types of attacks, actual attacks.
NOTE CONF
We're going to look at that.
What is an information security threat?
NOTE CONF
I think the most important thing and a lot of
people really struggle with this is getting the terminology right.
NOTE CONF
And we're not, we're not sort of being academic in
the sense that, hey, we need you to learn the
NOTE CONF
term terminology for the sake of being a good student.
I said, You cannot actually fight or you cannot actually
NOTE CONF
defend against an abstract risk.
If you want to defend your organization from real attacks,
NOTE CONF
you have to get very concrete about what is being
attacked and where you're going to put controls.
NOTE CONF
If you start saying abstract things like, and I mean
there's an example here, right?
NOTE CONF
So I like to give examples from home security rather
than IT security just to remove the whole technology dimension
NOTE CONF
so you can see something concrete that you can relate
to.
NOTE CONF
So the threat here is the possibility of somebody breaking
into your home.
NOTE CONF
The threat actor here is the burglar who actually carries
out the break-in.
NOTE CONF
So note the difference between the threat, which is like
a generic danger.
NOTE CONF
To the threat actor, which is the actual vehicle or
the actor that is carrying out that danger.
NOTE CONF
So here the threat actor is the burglar.
Then you've got the risk, which is the burglar exploiting
NOTE CONF
the lock on your front door to enter your home
to steal your asset.
NOTE CONF
Right, so you see the risk and we'll define it,
we'll define the risk very precisely when you get to
NOTE CONF
the weak on risk, but you'll see here that you've
got the threat actor there, you've got the asset there,
NOTE CONF
which is a 13 karat diamond.
You've got the vulnerability there, which is the lock, and
NOTE CONF
you've got the full pathway.
So how the actor exploited the vulnerability to get into
NOTE CONF
your home, to get access to the asset, that whole
pathway is a risk, and that's there.
NOTE CONF
So the, what's the threat vector?
The vector here is, what, how do they get in?
NOTE CONF
Right, how, so you've got the threat, which is the
danger of your home being generally broken into.
NOTE CONF
You've got the very specific burglar, but you need to
know what is the specific way they got in, because
NOTE CONF
if you don't know the specific way they got in,
you can't put in a specific control to stop them
NOTE CONF
from getting in.
Right?
NOTE CONF
Remember, security does not work in abstract terms, it works
in concrete terms.
NOTE CONF
So the threat vector is the locked, the entry through
the locked door.
NOTE CONF
And notice that if the risk was not the threat
actor picking the lock and going into your home and
NOTE CONF
stealing the diamond, but the threat actor walking through an
unlocked door, an unlocked front door rather than a locked
NOTE CONF
front door, is a different risk.
Why is there a different risk?
NOTE CONF
Same actor, same asset, same pathway generally.
The only difference is that the door was locked or
NOTE CONF
unlocked.
It's different because the vulnerability was different.
NOTE CONF
The vulnerability in one case was the lock was pickable.
In the second case, it was that the door was
NOTE CONF
left unlocked.
Those two scenarios, pickable lock, unlocked door, need two different
NOTE CONF
strategies.
For the pickable lock, you need a different lock that's
NOTE CONF
unpickable by the particular actor you're worried about.
And for the unlocked door, you need an arming system
NOTE CONF
to make sure that your doors remain locked when you
when you're not actually using it, when it should be
NOTE CONF
locked.
So if you can't tell the difference between locked and
NOTE CONF
unlocked doors in a risk, it means that you don't
know the difference between two security strategies.
NOTE CONF
There are different strategies So every different threat actor, every
different vulnerability, every different asset, combination of them, different risk
NOTE CONF
scenarios, each scenario, different strategy.
Yes, there will be some strategies, some scenarios that will
NOTE CONF
require the same type of strategy, you can cluster, but
if you can't get down to the leaf level and
NOTE CONF
distinguish them, you're gonna be in a bit of strife.
OK.
NOTE CONF
So why do threat actors attack organizations in the first
place?
NOTE CONF
Right.
There are a number of reasons.
NOTE CONF
The most obvious one is ransomware.
This is the one that everybody knows about.
NOTE CONF
Ransomware basically is an extortion type of attack where you
are locked out of your own IT systems and you're
NOTE CONF
basically asked to pay in order to get access to
them again, but that's not the only type.
NOTE CONF
There's a lot of other different types, right?
So stealing the resources of your organization might be information
NOTE CONF
is your resource.
Somebody comes in and steals your information because they need
NOTE CONF
it.
Maybe because the insider wanted revenge for a perceived.
NOTE CONF
Actual or perceived grievance.
Or because you have, you are in a trust relationship
NOTE CONF
with another organization, and that organization was the target, not
you.
NOTE CONF
So you got caught in the crossfire.
And then there are some more advanced ones that we
NOTE CONF
talked about here, which is a competitor trying to replicate
your capability, right?
NOTE CONF
They're trying to enter the market.
They don't know how to do what they need to
NOTE CONF
do to be able to produce the product or the
process or whatever it is they need to do.
NOTE CONF
You know how to do it, they want to steal
it, right.
NOTE CONF
And then there's the national security ones like cyber warfare.
You might be a military company or an SME providing
NOTE CONF
assistance or part of a supply chain in a national
security process or something, and you get attacked because the
NOTE CONF
attacker wants to compromise you or compromise the national security,
and you're getting caught up in that.
NOTE CONF
And that's sort of.
One is a bank, like a central bank.
NOTE CONF
If the bank goes down, people stop trusting the currency,
and that creates inflation.
NOTE CONF
So there's that side as well.
As more and more of the industry becomes digitized, more
NOTE CONF
of the things that we never considered to be cyber
related is becoming cyber related.
NOTE CONF
You can bring down electricity.
You can stop water from flowing.
NOTE CONF
You can do all these things because more and more
of the technology used to run these critical infrastructures is
NOTE CONF
digitized.
Now, um, threat actors are not all the same.
NOTE CONF
This is a very simple taxonomy.
You can divide the threat actors into malicious or accidental,
NOTE CONF
right?
So purposive and malicious being one, or non-purposive and accidental
NOTE CONF
being the other, right?
And it's kind of obvious why, you know, why you
NOTE CONF
would want to make a difference between the two.
A careless employee is an entirely different problem from an
NOTE CONF
attacker.
OK, so that distinction is important.
NOTE CONF
The second, If we now zoom into the militias, we
can divide militias into two categories organized and ad hoc.
NOTE CONF
Ad hoc are those script kiddies, disgruntled employees.
They're angry in the moment.
NOTE CONF
They don't have a plan.
They haven't been scheming for 6 months to a year.
NOTE CONF
They are, you know, a problem, but they're nowhere near
as dangerous as somebody who's got a plan.
NOTE CONF
So we make a distinction there.
This affects how you understand what people are going to
NOTE CONF
do in your organization, once they're in your organization, then
organized.
NOTE CONF
Can be divided into two Right, and organize here, we're
not thinking about teams of people, not just one individual,
NOTE CONF
right?
So here we have highly sophisticated and low sophisticated, which
NOTE CONF
I accept from a language point of view, isn't that
semantically helpful.
NOTE CONF
But we want to separate activists, right?
The, the, the individual comes with a bucket of paint
NOTE CONF
and throws it on your laptop, right?
2, Highly sophisticated teams, army, cyber army type people, so
NOTE CONF
hacktivists, insiders, low sophisticated insiders might in a very organized
way decide how to take information and sell it to
NOTE CONF
a third party because they want to hurt you, whatever.
They are nowhere near as dangerous as a nation state
NOTE CONF
setting up a military team.
610 people whose job it is to focus on cyber
NOTE CONF
attacks, big difference.
And then we would divide highly sophisticated into strategically and
NOTE CONF
operationally motivated teams.
There is a big difference between the highly sophisticated.
NOTE CONF
Now, um, why?
It's interesting to note that if you are attacked by
NOTE CONF
a team of hackers and they are motivated by their
own financial, you know, Reward Your job then as a
NOTE CONF
defender is to try to make it so expensive for
them to attack that they lose their motivation and they
NOTE CONF
go somewhere else, right?
But if you are attacked by a strategically motivated team,
NOTE CONF
mercenaries who are hired by a sponsor, you can make
it as expensive as you want.
NOTE CONF
They may give up, but their sponsor will not give
up.
NOTE CONF
They'll just replace them with another team.
And so one team gets replaced by another team, gets
NOTE CONF
replaced by another team, gets replaced by another team.
So there is no point trying to spend all of
NOTE CONF
your effort trying to defend against the hackers.
You've got to think who's sponsoring them and how can
NOTE CONF
you.
How can you change their mind?
NOTE CONF
Right.
Do you understand the difference between the two?
NOTE CONF
It is really important to distinguish because your whole strategy
for operation, for organized crime, for instance, is different too.
NOTE CONF
national security strategy, very different strategies.
You can just end up spending all your resources fighting
NOTE CONF
this hacker team, and then you think you're one, and
then here comes another attack and then another and another
NOTE CONF
and another, and you'll never know why until you have
enough threat intel to figure out who is sending these
NOTE CONF
people to me and why and what is their issue
and how can we figure out how to contact them
NOTE CONF
or how to.
Signal to them that we are not who you think
NOTE CONF
or uh maybe you should go somewhere else, right?
That messaging is not going to happen if you simply
NOTE CONF
don't know the difference between the team that's attacking you
and the team that's sponsoring you.
NOTE CONF
Enjoy sponsoring them.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Now, another very valuable uh slide.
This is 4 categories of threat actors across the verticals
NOTE CONF
from left to right.
It's the amateurs, then the hackers, then the insiders, and
NOTE CONF
then the advanced persistent threat.
This is the most organized and most sophisticated.
NOTE CONF
And what this, this mapping is on the vertical is
risk exposure to your firm.
NOTE CONF
On the horizontal is the ability of the threat actor,
the capability.
NOTE CONF
So risk exposure on the y axis, capability on the
x axis, and from left to right we're going from
NOTE CONF
least capable to most capable, and generally you're seeing.
As you go to the right, you're also going up.
NOTE CONF
So the least capable are the least you should be
worried about, least exposure to you, the most capable, the
NOTE CONF
most exposure to you.
But the red line is the most interesting line in
NOTE CONF
the graph.
The red line says there is a direct correlation between
NOTE CONF
the ability of the attacker to experiment around your defenses
and your exposure.
NOTE CONF
So if they are a curious hacker and they want
to learn about your defenses and they spend the time
NOTE CONF
learning about your defenses, then they are extremely dangerous.
If they are bored 14 year olds who are just
NOTE CONF
knocking on people's doors and will knock on the next
door after a short period of time, it's nothing to
NOTE CONF
worry about.
OK, you see the difference between the two.
NOTE CONF
Go back to the home security, if you spend a
million dollars setting up your home security, the most advanced
NOTE CONF
CCTV, biometrics, locks, 16-inch steel doors, walls, walls, roofs, floors,
everything is protected, and your attacker may not be very
NOTE CONF
sophisticated, but they sit outside your home on the other
side of the street, and they just sit there for
NOTE CONF
six months looking at you.
Right?
NOTE CONF
And they figure out that on weekends, you know, you
go, you go somewhere on Friday night, you come back
NOTE CONF
on Sunday morning, and you've got little kids and the
kids once in a while leave the side door open,
NOTE CONF
yeah.
You just walk in.
NOTE CONF
So if they're willing to learn, they will get in.
It's not related to how sophisticated your security is.
NOTE CONF
You see the relationship between experimental ability, experimentation, and penetration.
Yeah On the right hand side, the APT advanced actors
NOTE CONF
are dangerous because they go through this cycle.
They will collect intelligence about you.
NOTE CONF
They figure out your defenses.
They will find a way to get in their exploitation.
NOTE CONF
Once they get in, they will take control of the
environment.
NOTE CONF
They will mobilize.
Get the access they need to get to the assets
NOTE CONF
they need, and then they'll move to the next organization.
So that cycle when it's resourced and organized with a
NOTE CONF
team of people who have come together to take you
down, and the most advanced teams, they have software engineers
NOTE CONF
on the teams that made the firewalls that you use
to protect yourself.
NOTE CONF
So you buy all the software.
All these organizations buy software to defend themselves.
NOTE CONF
They don't make it themselves.
Those software, that software has bugs, and that software had
NOTE CONF
engineers behind the software.
So the most advanced teams have the engineers that wrote
NOTE CONF
your cyber defense software on the teams.
So Good luck, basically.
NOTE CONF
Now, taking it one step further.
There is a natural leverage or natural advantage that threat
NOTE CONF
actors have against any attacker has against a defender, and
these advantages are in the physical world, not in the
NOTE CONF
digital world.
We'll talk about the digital world in a moment.
NOTE CONF
So when an attacker anonymously out there in the wild
says, Hey, I'm going to attack your firm, the first
NOTE CONF
point is that they can decide when to attack you.
The timing of the attack is entirely within their control.
NOTE CONF
They also decide where to attack you.
So if it's your home, whether they should come in
NOTE CONF
through the front door, through the roof, to the right,
and the home is a bit simplistic.
NOTE CONF
If you are running, you know, a whole city, then
you can see the problem, right?
NOTE CONF
The location is a big, big question.
Where is the attack coming from?
NOTE CONF
That's in their control.
The third, they can decide what method to use to
NOTE CONF
attack you.
That means they're going to choose.
NOTE CONF
Well, I should have started from the beginning.
From a timing point of view, they're going to choose
NOTE CONF
a time when it's inconvenient for you, so attacking on
Christmas Day, right?
NOTE CONF
If you talk to any of the big banks, the
most, the biggest cyberattacks happen on public holidays, because they
NOTE CONF
know that there's a skeleton staff, everybody's gone, this is
the best time.
NOTE CONF
If you've ever gotten somebody trying, you know, you get
wake up in the morning at 6:00 a.m. or 7:00
NOTE CONF
a.m. whenever you wake up, and you get a message
saying, hey, somebody tried to access your account at 3:00
NOTE CONF
a.m., right, that 3:00 a.m. is not an accident.
Right, it's because they know you are not going to
NOTE CONF
be sitting on your computer, and if there are any
messages that come, for example, you know, here's a verification
NOTE CONF
code, you're not going to notice them for at least
2-3 hours, gives the person plenty of time, right?
NOTE CONF
So timing is in their hands, location, attack method, and
they can decide how long they need to prepare for
NOTE CONF
the attack before they do the first attack and before
you know the attack is coming.
NOTE CONF
OK, that's also in their hand and They know who
you are.
NOTE CONF
You don't know who they are.
And finally, If they're a small team of 5 people
NOTE CONF
or 10 people, they're going to use their entire team
in that attack.
NOTE CONF
You as an organization with 10,000 employees, you cannot use
10,000 employees in your defense.
NOTE CONF
You cannot bring 10,000 employees together and organize them in
a defensive campaign.
NOTE CONF
Simply trying to get everybody to even know that there
is an attack happening is hard enough, let alone employing
NOTE CONF
that leverage.
That's all Physical natural leverage.
NOTE CONF
If you go into the digital environment now and you
look at what does the digital environment do to add
NOTE CONF
more leverage or take away leverage, you find that this
gets multiplied, right?
NOTE CONF
So.
Attackers can attack you from anywhere in the world.
NOTE CONF
They can be sitting in the Antarctica.
All they need is an IP address and access to
NOTE CONF
the internet.
That's a massive advantage.
NOTE CONF
Once they're attacking a virus or malware starts to spread,
it spreads in seconds across your firm.
NOTE CONF
The speed of the attack is one of their biggest
leverage points, and your ability to defend your human decision
NOTE CONF
making cycle happens in days and weeks and months.
Right?
NOTE CONF
Their attack happens in seconds, your response happens in weeks.
That's a massive point of leverage for them as well,
NOTE CONF
right?
Your attack surface, massive attack surface, your mobile phones, your,
NOTE CONF
your laptops, all your devices, part of the attack surface.
They can attack and come in from anywhere, but, and
NOTE CONF
you don't even know how big your attack surface is,
especially if parts of your organization are buying IT and
NOTE CONF
and deploying it and not telling you, which happens in
a lot of banks, yeah.
NOTE CONF
So, how big is that attack surface?
How much does it cost to make a weapon in
NOTE CONF
the real world?
You're talking about a gun or anything.
NOTE CONF
If you make the cost of making a gun and
the cost of making a second gun, the cost is
NOTE CONF
still substantive every time you try to replicate a gun.
But in the digital environment, how much does it cost
NOTE CONF
to make a virus?
Expensive.
NOTE CONF
How much does it cost to copy a virus?
0.
NOTE CONF
I can make a million copies of a virus.
It cost me nothing.
NOTE CONF
It's an entirely different economic structure in the digital environment
to the physical environment.
NOTE CONF
So what I'm basically saying here is if you take
the natural leverage that the threat actor has and you
NOTE CONF
look at what the defender has to go through to
defend themselves, it's not a fair game.
NOTE CONF
It's not a level playing field.
And add to that that most organizations are burdened with
NOTE CONF
compliance.
Huge compliance requirements, they're under-resourced because they're a cost center,
NOTE CONF
not a revenue generator, the cyber teams, and there's a
skills gap, so you can't even get the right people
NOTE CONF
in your team.
It's a massive problem.
NOTE CONF
So now you see why incidents keep increasing, even though
the expenditure on cyber is also increasing.
NOTE CONF
OK, I'm not gonna go through um each of these
categories, but actually, I'll go through some of them just
NOTE CONF
to give you an idea.
In your textbook, there is a deep description of each
NOTE CONF
of these categories.
So, I suggest you go through, you should know what
NOTE CONF
they are, right?
If you go through a cyber, you know, degree or
NOTE CONF
a cyber subject, the very least you should know what
are the different types of attacks and the terminology used.
NOTE CONF
To, you know, to identify that attack.
So compromise to IP, I think we've spoken about that
NOTE CONF
a lot, piracy, infringement, software attacks, viruses, worms, etc.
etc.
NOTE CONF
um deviation in quality of service, you, you are a
small medium enterprise, you're connected via an ISP, your ISP
NOTE CONF
goes down.
No internet, that's an attack, and I should point out.
NOTE CONF
We look at accidents like attacks, so if it's lightning
or flood or fire that breaks out and it affects
NOTE CONF
your information resources, whether that's bringing down your IT systems
or whatever, it's an attack.
NOTE CONF
The English linguistic term like in the dictionary is purposive
malicious.
NOTE CONF
It's sort of intended there, but in security when we
say attack, we're talking about the form or the pattern
NOTE CONF
of events.
We're not talking about the intention here.
NOTE CONF
So an attack is something that affects negatively your assets,
whether it was done accidentally or done maliciously is not
NOTE CONF
the issue.
That's more about profiling and trying to figure out what
NOTE CONF
the attacker is going to do next so you can
defend better.
NOTE CONF
But the classification of whether something is an attack or
not is not related to intent.
NOTE CONF
It's related to the pattern of activity.
So espionage or trespass.
NOTE CONF
That doesn't really need explanation.
Somebody's trying to steal information for whatever reason, forces of
NOTE CONF
nature.
I just talked about human error failure, accidents, an employee
NOTE CONF
makes a mistake, sends you a huge amount of money
to the wrong account, bank account is happening a lot
NOTE CONF
nowadays.
I think they're all really straightforward, um, examples on the
NOTE CONF
right and categories on the left.
And in terms of The vectors, the actual, you know,
NOTE CONF
behavior of the attacking entity, it's like, you know, scan.
A piece of software can scan the environment and start
NOTE CONF
infecting things.
It can send a huge amount of garbage and shut,
NOTE CONF
you know, gag things.
It can, it can be a problem for you because
NOTE CONF
the software had a back door, and they left the
back door in either accidentally or deliberately, and somebody else
NOTE CONF
discovers it and then enters your organization that way.
And this is like a huge thing, right, for example,
NOTE CONF
ANZ Bank spends a huge amount of money on when
they buy software, putting it in a sandbox and then
NOTE CONF
testing it out to make sure that there's no back
door or unintended consequence of using it before they deploy
NOTE CONF
it in a production environment, and they were saying to
me they spend more on the testing of the software
NOTE CONF
and when they put the software into the environment to
test whether the environment works properly than they do in
NOTE CONF
buying the environment.
So the technology, the firewalls, ID systems, all that, they,
NOTE CONF
by the way, buy from 3 different vendors because they
don't trust any vendor, and it's really interesting is that
NOTE CONF
when you buy from 3 separate ecosystems of vendors, you
raise the bar on the hackers.
NOTE CONF
Right, because the hackers now, if they can get into,
if they know a lot about one vendor because they
NOTE CONF
spent all their time knowing the ins and outs of
it, if they enter an environment which doesn't rely on
NOTE CONF
one vendor, it really raises the bar on them.
So they need people on the team that understand all
NOTE CONF
the vendors, right, or as many as you've used, which
makes the number of people that can attack you very
NOTE CONF
limited.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
OK, so I'm not gonna talk about the Horizon Teaching
case, except to say that um How many of you
NOTE CONF
have read it OK.
Like the whole thing or just this week's?
NOTE CONF
The whole thing, yeah.
So the, the, I hope you found the, the story
NOTE CONF
interesting.
The story was actually written around the lectures, right?
NOTE CONF
So in these 1st 6 weeks, uh, 1st 6 scenes,
you're going to see a lot of the themes that
NOTE CONF
we talked about in the story.
So read the story as it is an example of
NOTE CONF
what you have learned in the lectures colliding with real
life, OK.
NOTE CONF
And in the actual tutorials this week, you'll be asked
to talk about, to identify, I think, 3.
NOTE CONF
Three of the key insights that come to you, and
then an asset threat pair that you can identify from
NOTE CONF
the story.
What is, what is the, give me, give us any
NOTE CONF
pairing of assets and threats that explain what the problem
is that this organization is undergoing.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Fantastic.
NOTE CONF
Perfect timing.
Any questions before I As I promised, I've got an
NOTE CONF
exam to administer in exactly 15 minutes, so this is
going to end early, but I've got a few minutes
NOTE CONF
to take any questions if there are any.
Yes.
NOTE CONF
For the assignment, it seems like what you picked in
your example is quite narrow.
NOTE CONF
Is it better to go narrow in detail rather than
a broader idea?
NOTE CONF
No, I just chose a narrow.
It's no better.
NOTE CONF
If you can articulate a really compelling case, then whether
it's broad and if it's 1 inch deep ocean wide
NOTE CONF
or 1 mile deep, you know, really the tutors will
be able to compensate.
NOTE CONF
OK, fantastic.
I'll see you next week.
NOTE CONF
So I Yeah, yeah.
So whether that's what it could be more, but 11
NOTE CONF
of these, yeah, actually I missed the part like, uh,
you said lines, uh, like not related to their intent
NOTE CONF
but to the pattern.
What was that?
NOTE CONF
No, that means that that means that when you, when
we say something of an attack, it can be an
NOTE CONF
accident.
Yeah, it's the fact that the accident led to impact,
NOTE CONF
not whether the accident was deliberate or not.
OK, OK, so accidentally everything is an attack.
NOTE CONF
harms the assets, it's an attack, not it's an accident
or not.
NOTE CONF
That's not the issue.
It's an attack.
NOTE CONF
That's all.
Thank you, Professor, regarding next week's quiz.
NOTE CONF
the workshop, um, is it going to be discussed today
during the tutorial as well?
NOTE CONF
Uh, no.
Why would we discuss it in the, as in like,
NOTE CONF
uh, the details of the, like, how about the quiz
itself?
NOTE CONF
Like, is it it's multiple choice, choice, and it's on
paper on paper.
NOTE CONF
Paper on paper.
OK, thank you so much.
NOTE CONF
And the material is just from week 1, week 3.
It'll be like anything up until the week 4.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, anything up until week 4.
Thank you.
NOTE CONF
Basically for the assignment, I had a manager.
Yeah, that's a kind of analysis to get his feedback.
NOTE CONF
You can get his feedback.
I mean, the point at the end of the day
NOTE CONF
is if he's going to give you an idea on
what the pitch, right, reference it in your references that
NOTE CONF
you did.
Thank you.
NOTE CONF
by Yes.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
You can move to any class as long as your
tutor agrees and you stick to it.
NOTE CONF
No problem.
OK.
NOTE CONF
want to win.
T.
NOTE CONF
I'm very important.
Yeah, really.
NOTE CONF
How are you bro?
Do you have another?
NOTE CONF
I do.
Uh, yeah, let's go.
NOTE CONF
Can I come with you?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, let's go.
NOTE CONF
You got the food, yeah, yeah, I got the food.
When I first day arrived in Melbourne, so I feel
NOTE CONF
it's pretty uncomfortable.
So it's first day in Melbourne, too bad.
NOTE CONF
I.
How many of I Yes.
NOTE CONF
Thank you.
No.
NOTE CONF
I couldn't tell you.
I know.
NOTE CONF
Oh yeah Did.
I you.
NOTE CONF
You just add extra.
I need to check that.
NOTE CONF
Margo, let's go.
How I see you.
NOTE CONF
Thanks.
How are you?
NOTE CONF
I didn't realize Lecture for the next class.
The uh And Looking me up and startled me.
NOTE CONF